Guide to the Dutch and French Engravings (Portraits and Allegories), circa 1509-1778.
Dutch and French engravings (portraits and allegories)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Dutch and French engravings (portraits and allegories), circa 1509-1778.
8451
0.3 cubic feet (approximately 89 items).
Engravings
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Engravings by various artists, depicting prominent individuals, including many clergymen and intellectuals, of western Europe in the 16th-18th centuries. Also, allegorical scenes, Biblical scenes, and decorative vignettes.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Engravings by various artists, depicting prominent individuals, including many clergymen and intellectuals, of western Europe in the 16th-18th centuries. Many of the portraits appear to have been done in memory of their subjects shortly after their death. Included are portraits of Thomas Cromwell, Gabriel Naudé, Nicolas Caussin; John Tillotson, Archbishop of Canterbury; Jean de La Fontaine; Alexandre de Prouville, marquis de Tracy; Giovanni Battista Montano, Thierry Bignon, Edouard Colbert de Villacerf, Pierre-Daniel Huet, and Pierre Gassendi. Also included are allegorical scenes, Biblical scenes, and decorative vignettes. One engraving, "La reponce embarassante," 1700s, is hand-colored. Engravers include Nicolas de Largillierre, Claude Mellan, Robert Nanteuil, Abraham Bosse, Jacobus Houbraken, and Gerard de Jode.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Caussin, Nicolas, 1583-1651; Cromwell, Thomas, Earl of Essex, 1485?-1540; Naudé, Gabriel, 1600-1653; Tillotson, John, 1630-1694; La Fontaine, Jean de, 1621-1695; Tracy, Alexandre de Prouville, marquis de, 1596 or 1603-1670; Montano, Giovanni Battista, 1545-1621; Bignon, Thierry; Villacerf, Edouard Colbert de; Huet, Pierre-Daniel, 1630-1721; Gassendi, Pierre, 1592-1655; Largillierre, Nicolas de, 1656-1746; Mellan, Claude, 1598-1688; Nanteuil, Robert, 1623-1678; Bosse, Abraham, 1602-1676; Houbraken, Jacobus, 1698-1780; Jode, Gerard de, 1509-1591
Form and Genre Terms:
Engravings--France.; Engravings--Netherlands.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Philippus Theobaldus, 18th Century; 1.1 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Engraver unknown but most likely made in France.
  Information from Captions: Lived 1638-1663. Did work in Gaul (modern day France/Belgium).
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin.
- Gabriel Naudé, 1.2 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Cl. Mellan G. del. et sc. Cartel.
  Information from Captions: Born in Paris, February 2, 1600. Died in Abbeville, July 29, 1653.
  Additional Information: Original description in French.
- Sébastien Antoine Slodtz, 18th Century; 1.3 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Designed by Cochin le Fils, Engraved by L. Cars
  Information from Captions: Designer of the king's cabinet.
  Additional Information: Original description In French. Lived 1699-1771.
- P. Nicolas Caussin of the Company of Jesus, 1.4 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in French. Lived 1583-1951.
- R.P. Joseph of Paris, 1.5 (Box 1)
  Information from Captions: Capuchin preacher, Died December 18, 1638.
  Additional Information: Original description in French. Lived 1577-1638.
- Mathieu Molé, 1.6 (Box 1)
  Information from Captions: First Presidential Garde of Seals. Born 1584, Died January 3, 1656, at the age of 72.
- Charles de Créqui, 1633; 1.7 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Claude Mellan
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Original from copperplate engraving.
- Agatha Castillionea [de Chastillon], wife of Claude of Marolles, 1.8 (Box 1)
  Information from Captions: Died August (3?), 1630
- Petrus Gassendus [Pierre Gassendi], 1.9 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1592-1655.
- Raphael Menicucius, 17th Century; 1.10 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1598-1688
- [Stefano da Cessena], 1674; 1.11 (Box 1)
- Jean François de Gondy (Gondi), Archbishop of Paris, 1.12 (Box 1)
  Engraver: M. Lasne
  Additional Information: Original description in French. Years: 1613-1679
- R.P. Carolus Faure (Charles Faure, who restored the canonical rule of St geneviève), 1.13 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1594-1652
- Leonard Philaras, [diplomat], 17th Century; 1.14 (Box 1)
  Information from Captions: Born in Athens, sent to the court of Louis XIII by the Dukeof Parma.
- Leonard Philaras [diplomat], 17th Century; 1.15 (Box 1)
- R. P. Nicolas Caussin, 1651; 1.16 (Box 1)
  Information from Captions: Jesuit
  Additional Information: Original description in French. Years:1583-1651
- St James, 1.17 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: No description.
- Jean Fronteau, 1663; 2.1 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Robert Nanteuil
  Information from Captions: F. Cabouret commissioned the engraving after Fronteau's death.
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. French cleric. Years: 1614-1662
- Johannes Saenredam [Jan Saerendam, engraver], 1602; 2.2 (Box 1)
  Information from Captions: His fatherland/patria is listed as Sardamum. He is a disciple of Golzi, an imitator of Lysippus (an ancient sculptor).
- Abraham Grass, 1668; 2.3 (Box 1)
- Mme D'Escorailles de Roussille, Duchesse de Fontanges, 1681; 2.4 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in French. The proper name may be Marie Angélique, the lover of Louis the Sun King.
- Paulus Petavius [Paul Petau, publisher and book collector], 1610; 2.5 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Isaac Briot
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1568-1614
- [Charles Loyseau, jurist], 2.6 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Iaspar Isac
- Adolph, Count of Schwarzenberg, 1600-1650; 2.7 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in German.
- Jacques Callot, 2.8 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in French. Years: 1592-1635
- [Duchess of Lenox?], 1642; 2.9 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Wenceslaus Hollar
- Baur [or Bauer], Painter, 1637; 2.10 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Johann Wilhelm Baur
- Francisco Floro Anverpiano, Painter (Frans Floris of Antwerp), 2.11 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. If it is Frans Floris, his years are 1517-1570.
- J. Meyer, Painter, 1769; 2.12 (Box 1)
  Engraver: P. Falconet
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin, other details in English.
- Denise, Fille de (Daughter of) Jean Camusat et Femme de (Wife of) Pierre le Petit, 2.13 (Box 1)
  Engraver: A. Trouvain (1656-1707)
  Information from Captions: Died November 22, 1675.
- Franciscus Pinssonius [François Pinsson Des Riolles], 2.14 (Box 1)
- M. Morett, 2.15 (Box 1)
- Hendrick de Keyser, 1621; 2.16 (Box 1)
  Engraver: I.Suyderhoff
  Information from Captions: Born May 15, 1565, Died May 15, 1621.
- Hippolytus Feret, 2.17 (Box 1)
  Engraver: A. Trouvain (possibly)
- Jacob Tyken, 2.18 (Box 1)
- John Tillotson Archbishop of Canterbury, 1746; 3.1 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Jacobus Houbraken
  Additional Information: Original description in English. Years: 1630-1694.
- William of Wickham, Bishop of Winchester, 1738; 3.2 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in English. Years: 1324-1404.
- Henry Stafford, Duke of Buckingham, 1747; 3.3 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in English. Years: 1455-1483.
- George Savile, Marquis of Hallifax, 1740; 3.4 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in English. Years: 1633-1695.
- Thomas Cromwell, Earl of Essex, 1739; 3.5 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in English. Years: 1485(?)-1540
- Jean de la Fontaine, 4.1 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Ficquet
  Additional Information: Years: 1621-1695.
- Jean de la Fontaine, 4.2 (Box 1)
- Lodovico Ariosto, 1773; 4.3 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Years: 1474-1533.
- Françoise d'Aubigné, Marquise de Maintenon, 1719; 4.4 (Box 1)
  Engraver: E.Ficquet
  Additional Information: Years: 1635 (Baptized) -1719.
- Fénelon, 4.5 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Years: 1651-1715.
- Father Dominic of Jesus Maria, of the Order of Carmes, 1621; 5.1 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Mebager?
  Information from Captions: Aged 63 in 1621
- J. Le Saige, 5.2 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Nicolas Regnesson
- Sir Samuel Barnardiston of Brightnel, 1700; 5.3 (Box 1)
  Engraver: R. White (?)
  Information from Captions: Born June 23, 1620; Died November 8, 1707.
  Additional Information: Original description in English.
- Keraudrun, 1659; 5.4 (Box 1)
  Engraver: I. Frosne
- Marquis Alexandre de Prouville de Tracy, 1660; 5.5 (Box 1)
- Unknown, 5.6 (Box 1)
- Paulus Praun, 5.7 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Lichtensbeger
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1548-1616.
- Felix van Sambix, 18th century; 5.8 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Michiel Jansz. van Mierevelt
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1553-1642.
- Henry (Henri) de Bourbon, Prince of Condé, 5.9 (Box 1)
  Engraver: I. Honervogt
- Ioannes Baptista Montana [sic] [= Giovanni Battista Montano, architect and engraver], 1621; 5.10 (Box 1)
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1534-1621.
- Johannes Michael Dilherrus, 5.11 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Jacob Sandrart
- Thomas Howard, 21st Earl of Arundel in Surrey, 18th century; 5.12 (Box 1)
  Engraver: J.L. Krafft
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Years: 1585-1646.
- Theodoricus [Thierry] Bignon, magistrate, numismatist, and art collector, 1697; 5.13 (Box 1)
  Engraver: P.Van Schuppen
  Information from Captions: Died January 19, 1697 at 65.
- Théologie, 6.1A (Box 1)
  Engraver: de Troy + Van Schuppen
  Information from Captions: 1632-1697
  Additional Information:
- Géometrie, 6.1B (Box 1)
- Astronomie, 6.1C (Box 1)
- Diligence, 1552; 6.2 (Box 1)
  Engraver: German School
- Unknown, 6.3 (Box 1)
- Illustrious and Powerful Prince Charles of Great Britain, 6.4 (Box 1)
- Unknown, 6.5 (Box 1)
- Unknown, 1550; 6.6 (Box 1)
  Engraver: Étienne Delaune
- Edouard Colbert [de Villacerf], 1696; 1A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Largillière + Gérard Edelinck
- Petrus Daniel Huetius, Episcopus Suessionensis [Pierre-Daniel Huet, scholar, antiquary], 1686; 2A (Box 1)
- Series of Four Engravings, Possibly Venus and Cupid, 1638; 3A (Box 1)
- Allegory of Europe, 17th century; 4A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Abraham Bosse?
- The Last Judgement, 1509 or 1517-1591; 5A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Gerard de Jode
- Tempus, Ver, Aestas, Autumnus, Hyems, 1565; 6A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Philippe Galle
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. The personification of Time, winged and seated, surrounded with various attributes, riding atop a chariot carried by two deer, destroying everything on his way; accompanied by personifications of the four seasons on foot (they are labeled: Autumnus, Hijems, Aestas, Ver); ruins of classical buildings are seen in the background. -Adapted from British Museum.
- The Martyrdom of Christ and the Apostles (Series title), 1577 - 1582; 7A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Hendrick Goltzius
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Matthias is beheaded with an ax and stoned the left of the scene of his martyrdom, he is shown again, with an ax in one hand and a book in the other. Among the show twice latin two lines. This print is part of a series of 13 prints of Christ (unnumbered) and the apostles (numbered), more specifically the torture they suffered.
- Summer, 1563; 8A (Box 1)
- Appearances of Christ after his death (Series title), 1583 - 1585; 9A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Julius Goltzius
  Additional Information: Original description in Latin. Appearances of Christ after his death (series title). Christ, dressed as a pilgrim, accompanies two apostles on the road to Emmaus. In the background a castle. The print has a signature Latin and is part of a series of prints on the subject of the appearances of Christ after his death.
- S. Onofrius, 1574; 10A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Johannes Sadeler I, Flemish
- Unknown, 11A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Joan. Collaert
- Samson and Delilah, 12A (Box 1)
- The Animals Going into the Ark from The Story of the Family of Seth, 1586; 13A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Johannes Sadeler I
- Repentant Sinners from the Old and New Testament, 1580-1590; 14A (Box 1)
- The Triumphs?, 15A (Box 1)
- Adam digging in the earth after the Fall, 16th century; 16A (Box 1)
- Jesus Consoling Mary Magdalene After His Resurrection, 17th century; 17A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Maarten de Vos
- La Reponce embarasante (The Embarassing Response), 1787; 18A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Brion + Chapuy
  Additional Information: Original title in French.
- Unknown, 17th century; 19A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Brebiette Pierre (?-very similar style)
- Pan, Nereids, and Tritons; Marine Triumphs 5, 17th century; 19B (Box 1)
  Engraver: Brebiette Pierre
- Unknown, 17th century; 20A (Box 1)
- Triumph of Galatea, 17th century; 20B (Box 1)
- Toilet of Thetis, 17th century; 21A (Box 1)
- Bacchanal, 17th century; 22A (Box 1)
- Unknown, 17th century; 23A (Box 1)
  Engraver: Abraham Bosse
- Unknown, 17th century; 23B (Box 1)
- Unknown, 17th century; 23C (Box 1)
- Venus and Cupid?, 1637; 24A (Box 1)
- Venus and Neptune, 17th century; 25A (Box 1)
- Venus and Cupid, 17th century; 25B (Box 1)
- Venus(?), 17th century; 25C (Box 1)